- Welcome back to "US
Government and Politics".
In a previous lesson,
we looked at how a person
can become a normal citizen
and eventually ascend to the presidency.
However, in-between those
steps there's campaigning.
And campaigning is expensive.
You need to travel around, hold rallies,
send out mailers.
A lot of different things that
take cash in order to do it.
So where do they get this money?
And what's legal and
what's not acceptable?
We can look at Buckley v. Valeo
in 1976, the Supreme Court case,
to get a sense of where
the judicial branch
thinks the line is.
The issue was that FECA's
limit on campaign spending
violated the 1st Amendment
right to free speech.
Now what the heck is FECA?
That's the Federal Election
Campaign Act of 1971.
And that said there's a limit on spending.
You need to disclose who's
giving you the money.
And that the IRS is gonna step in
and be a little bit of a public advocate
and basically level the playing field
in terms of how much money
candidates can receive from
donors and then actually spend.
So this case was saying,
do those limitations
violate the 1st Amendment right to speech?
The Supreme court said, yes.
That by limiting campaign spending
Congress had violated
people's right to free speech,
because donating money to a candidate
was seen by the Supreme
court as free speech.
I'm exercising what I think is right
via the giving of that money.
The court also said
that spending money to influence elections
is a form of constitutionally
protected speech.
And that FECA's limitations
on that spending
was a violation of constitutional rights.
However, the controversy
around campaign finance
has not abated.
In 2002, we can see the
McCain Feingold Act,
also known as the Bipartisan
Campaign Reform Act or BCRA.
This did a number of things
in order to try to reign in spending
and make sure it's a little
bit more transparent.
You know where the money's
coming from and fair.
Number one, it banned
something called soft money.
This soft money is unregulated.
There aren't limits on it,
there aren't laws on it.
You don't really know
what's going on exactly.
And the key thing about it,
is it doesn't go to a specific candidate.
So it can be used to push
forward a certain policy
or a perspective, but
it's not to this person.
It also limited hard money.
This is money that is federally regulated
and it goes to a specific
candidate or campaign.
So I'm saying, "This is
my money, it's $2,000
"and it's going to Mrs. X."
It also limited the
use of corporate money.
So it's money coming
directly from businesses
to fund ads that discuss political issues
within 60 days of a general election,
or 30 days of a primary.
Remember back to a previous lesson,
a primary is how a person
becomes the nominee
from a certain party.
They're putting a time limit on.
So you can't have six months of ads
that are funded by a corporation.
Finally, if you produced a negative ad,
something that was against
a specific candidate
or said something negative about them,
you would have to put your name on it.
You would say this ad
was produced by whoever.
They wanted that transparency.
They wanted a limit on the
amount of money that was spent,
the time in which those
ads could be produced.
And if it's negative,
you actually have to
put your name behind it,
so you can't hide behind a pseudonym.
One of the most critical
Supreme court cases
that we're gonna look
at in this entire course
deals with campaign finance.
It's specifically Citizens United
v. the Federal Election Commission.
And it happened in 2010.
Citizens United is a
nonprofit conservative group
and they wanted to advance a documentary
that they thought depicted
Hillary Clinton, accurately.
Other people would say depicted
her negatively or falsely.
So they said we should be able to spend
as much money as we want
pushing forth this documentary.
Federal Election Commission said
you can't do that by the BCRA.
Remember that McCain Feingold Act
that limited the amount of
money when ads could be run,
and if you have to add
your name to a negative ad.
This was challenged
and went all the way up
to the Supreme court.
The main issue is, does the BCRA
violate the 1st Amendment
right to free speech?
The Citizens United have the right
to put forth that documentary and fund it
and say whatever they want.
Is that their constitutionally
protected right?
The Supreme court says, yes,
Citizens United, which is
technically a corporation
has the right to free speech,
the same as an individual.
The Supreme court base this upon
there's prior restraint on
political speech via the BCRA.
You may remember prior restraint
from when we talked about media
and what can be said
and what cannot be said.
Is basically saying, if
this is gonna harm somebody
you can't put out that story.
And the Supreme court is saying,
prior restraint cannot
be used in this case.
Citizens United can say what they want.
If they want to fund that documentary,
that's their business.
And if it ends up hurting Hillary Clinton
that does not outweigh Citizens
United right to free speech.
When would the ban have been acceptable?
If the corporate spending was
likely to lead to corruption.
To prevent corruption,
the organization may not
coordinate with the candidate.
So, if Citizens United was giving
$2 million in a duffle bag to candidate X,
then this may lead to candidate X
taking on policies that
would benefit Citizens United
in a quid pro quo, essentially corruption.
Therefore the Supreme court
would say, that's not allowed.
But because it's not a
direct handing of money
from Citizens United to a
candidate in that manner,
that this is allowed under free speech.
Citizens United has really changed the way
that campaign finance is done since 2010.
So let's recap what we talked about today.
In 1974, you have FECA.
This is the Federal Election
Commission Campaign Act.
This put limits on the amount of money
that an individual can
give to a candidate.
It also limited the total amount
that a candidate was allowed to spend,
and it required contributions
to be disclosed.
It's very important transparency
who's giving money to who.
Luckily the Valeo struck down the limits
on campaign spending by a candidate.
We're saying that's an important part
of the election process
the Supreme court ruled.
In 2002, we had the Bipartisan
Campaign Reform Act,
also known as the McCain Feingold Act.
This banned soft money,
limited the use of
corporate and union money,
and limited hard money.
We're really gonna
focus on this corporate.
In 2010, the Supreme court
said that wasn't allowed.
That BCRA ended up violating
the 1st Amendment right to free speech,
even by a corporation.
In this instance, Citizens United.
This has changed the amount of money
that's in federal elections,
as we're gonna see in future lessons.
And has a direct consequence
on how politics are conducted
in the United States.