(upbeat music)
- Welcome back to US
government and politics.
In previous lessons, we've
looked at the important role
that the executive branch plays
in the overall government.
Today we're gonna see how someone goes
from being a normal citizen to
actually becoming president.
The first step in the process is someone
announcing their intention
to run for president.
This literally is the
first step in the process
and is all that needs to be done.
Often people stand in front
of some grand building,
or the house that they grew up in,
or they come down a golden escalator.
But what's really important is they said,
I'm throwing my hat into the ring,
I am gonna put forth
my name for president.
The next step in the process
is where elections actually
start getting held.
This is where the various parties,
remember the Republicans and the Democrats
are the two main ones,
are gonna figure out
who's gonna represent their party
in the race to be president.
Primaries, which happen in 80% of states,
can be closed, which means you have to be
an announced member of that
party in order to vote,
or they can be open, which
means anybody in the state,
whether you're Republican or Democrat,
can vote in that primary process.
20% of the states have
something called caucuses.
It's a little bit of a
different process where people
come together and they vote
by holding their hands up,
and verbal processes,
and things like that.
You don't need to know the ins and outs,
just know that it serves the main purpose,
which is that state's
party is gonna decide
who they think should be
the nominee from each party.
Next we go to nominating conventions.
This is where all the
votes from the primaries
and/or caucuses are tallied
up, and each party will say
this is the person that the
Democrat party puts forward
as their presidential nominee,
or the Republicans put forth
as their presidential nominee.
There's a lot of hoopla,
balloons, people glad handing,
and kissing babies, and
saying isn't this great,
we're gonna win, it's gonna be fantastic.
But a lot of it is getting set up
before the general election.
There's gonna be campaigning
Basically from as soon as
candidates officially announce,
they're gonna start campaigning,
which is they're gonna start
running advertisements,
getting out and seeing people.
If you've ever seen the weird scenes
when people go to Iowa and the state fair
and they all eat a hot dog,
that's because they're running for office.
They're hoping that people see them
and say that person is a good
leader, that person knows me,
and knows what I care
about, and therefore,
they would be a good person
to represent me as president.
The general election,
which is the first Tuesday
of November of every four
years, so it was in 2020,
now it's gonna be in 2024,
then 2028, and so on,
is where the president
is actually decided.
People go to the polls and they vote
for who they think should be president.
Then, each state will
put forward the votes
that they have via the electoral college,
and those are all counted up,
and the person with over 270
votes in the electoral
college becomes the president.
That one's a little bit tricky.
It's not just the person
with the most votes,
the popular vote winner,
that becomes president.
The electoral college is key.
Let's look at that via a map.
So if you've never heard
of the electoral college,
you'd say, shouldn't the
person who has one more vote
than the other person become president?
That's what a popular vote is,
and some nations do have that,
but the United States has
the electoral college.
And this was instituted as a
compromise in the Constitution,
remember that, very important
document we've talked about?
In order to make sure
that the biggest states
don't have all the power, that
some of the smaller states
also play a role in an election like this.
So, each state is gonna
have an apportioned amount
of electoral votes based
upon how many people
they have in the House of Representatives
and how many senators they have.
And remember, every
state has two senators,
but the number of people that they have
in the House of Representatives
depends on the population of that state.
So California's gonna
have 55 electoral votes
'cause they have 53 seats in the House.
Texas has 38 'cause they
have 36 seats in the House.
Remember, 38 minus their two senators.
Some of the other big population states
that we want to be aware of;
Florida with 29, New York with 29.
These are ones that are really gonna dwarf
the smaller states, such as
Wyoming, Montana, North Dakota,
they all have three, in terms
of their influence on
the electoral college.
However, some of them
are called swing states,
which is because they're
a little bit more purple.
So rather than consistently
red, like these states here,
they're typically gonna
vote for Republicans
and red is used as the color
to represent Republicans.
This is 2020, when the
incumbent President Trump
was running against former
Vice President Biden,
now President Biden, and blue states
are gonna be Democratic states.
Typically California is gonna go Democrat,
typically Washington and
Oregon, typically the Northeast.
Not always, but generally
those are gonna be blue states.
However, there are some swing states
that play a crucial role
in the electoral college.
They're Michigan, Wisconsin, Pennsylvania,
and then it was Ohio and Florida,
but they've gone a little
bit more red recently.
So, Republicans have been winning them
the past couple of elections.
What we wanna know is,
within these states,
the popular vote matters, obviously.
If you win Florida by one
vote, you win that state.
But then Florida submits their 29 votes
to the electoral college,
and those all get added up for each state.
The person that reaches
270 becomes the president.
In 2020, President Biden
got 306 electoral votes,
you could count up all these blue states.
And then President Trump got 232,
you can count up all the red states.
The last thing I wanna mention for this
is there's two states that
vote by congressional district.
So rather than just tallying
up the votes in their state
and saying our electoral
college goes to this candidate,
it could be different depending on
the district of the state,
so let's look at it.
Nebraska has five congressional districts.
They're gonna say four, at least in 2020,
of those congressional districts
think President Trump
should be president again.
One, Omaha, thinks that President
Biden should be president.
Therefore, Nebraska submits
four electoral votes
for President Trump and one
for Vice President Biden
at that time, now president.
Maine is gonna do something similar.
They have four congressional districts,
and in that case, three of those districts
went for Biden and one went for Trump.
So again, it's important
to know popular vote
for the states, then
become electoral college,
you need 270 to become president.
The last thing we're gonna
mention is the advantages
that an incumbent president has,
incumbent meaning that's
the president at the time.
So in 2020, it would've
been President Trump.
In 2024, if President
Biden decides to run again,
it will be President Biden.
Some of these advantages are,
they already have name recognition.
If you listen to the
news, you're gonna hear
President Biden, President
Biden, President Biden a lot
because the policies that he makes,
or executive actions or laws
that he signs into being,
or just whatever he's doing on that day,
the news is gonna report on.
So you hear that name a lot,
it's gonna resonate with people.
Number two, that's free publicity.
President Biden doesn't need to pay
those news companies to
actually say his name,
they're already doing so in the course
of reporting on what's
going on in the country.
So that free publicity
is gonna be helpful.
And number three, something
called franking privileges.
What this is is it allows lawmakers
to send materials to citizens.
The founders wanted this
so that the lawmakers
could directly communicate
with their citizens.
But as you send stuff to your citizens,
you can include things
that make you look good.
If you saw the stimulus
checks that went out,
they had President Trump's
signature on the bottom.
This associates the money
that went into people's
pockets with President Trump.
This is obviously beneficial to him,
and that's perfectly legal.
Because he's currently in
office, he can send things
to the citizens, key
thing, at taxpayer expense.
So he doesn't need to pay
for it outta his own pocket,
the taxpayers pay for it.
These three things represent
the incumbency advantages.
That's why, over the past 40 years or so,
there's only been two presidents,
the first President Bush
and President Trump,
that have not won reelection
and served two terms.
So today we've looked at the
steps for a person to announce
their intention to run and
actually become president.
We've looked at the electoral college,
specifically using 2020.
And we've looked at the
advantages of an incumbent.
Hopefully it gives you a better sense
of how a person becomes president
and what role you play
in that whole process.