- Welcome back to US
Government and Politics.
In previous lessons, we've looked at PACs,
specifically political action committees.
These are groups of
people that come together
in order to fund campaigns
to propagate issues that
they think are important.
Today we're gonna look at interest groups.
They're a little bit different,
but they're also consequential.
(chill music)
Interest groups are technically
organizations of people,
so groups of people that come together,
who share similar causes or concerns.
So they've got issues
that they wanna advance.
These can be broad,
as in very wide,
or very narrow,
a specific thing that
they think is important
and they wanna get it
passed by the government.
They try to influence the government
in order to address
those specific problems.
They influence via
something called lobbying.
This is when they try to put
pressure on the government,
that Senator or House of
Representative member,
and it could be positive
pressure or negative pressure,
such as we're gonna primary you.
If you don't do this
we're gonna have somebody else
run and try to replace you.
Or if you do this, we can
contribute to your campaign
and make sure that you remain popular
with your constituents.
Third, this is protected
via the First Amendment,
specifically, the ability to assemble.
So the same way that you
can come together in a march
you can come together
in an interest group.
So let's talk about some of
these different types of interest groups.
It could be something from labor unions,
and these would address
conditions of working people,
such as safety, hours, and compensation.
Some of the bigger ones are AFL-CIO.
They were separate labor unions,
but they actually merged in 1955.
We can also look at business organizations
and these interest
groups are gonna promote
the collective interest of business,
and they're generally
gonna oppose regulation
and legislation that
promotes workers' rights,
'cause they really try to
represent the business community.
This is such as the US
Chamber of Congress,
which actually has 3 million members.
They promote a wide variety of issues.
Also the National
Association of Manufacturers.
Then we can have
professional organizations,
and they're gonna address anything
that that group of people wants,
such as the American Bar
Association for lawyers,
or the American Medical
Association, AMA, for doctors.
Then we have agricultural organizations.
These address farms and large
scale agricultural issues,
such as the American
Farm Bureau Federation.
Environmental groups,
such as the Sierra Club,
Greenpeace, or Environmental Defense Fund
are gonna advance
environmental protections
in order to protect the planet
and fight climate change.
Then you've got single issue groups.
These are like single issue voters,
but they're groups of those voters.
They think that one specific concern
really overrides everything else.
You can look at this with NOW,
the National Association
of Women, or the NAACP.
Finally we've got
government interest groups.
These are groups of representatives
or state and local officials
who will come together in
some type of an organization
in order to push forward policies
and issues that they think are important.
You can look at this with
the National Governor's Association.
So obviously there's
many, many, many different
interest groups,
but not all are gonna be equal
in terms of their size or influence.
For example, some interest
groups have access
to more money than others.
Via this money they can fund projects,
they can advertise,
and really try to influence legislation
in their favor in a greater way.
Some interest groups have
more access to politicians
and other decision makers.
So when they pick up the phone,
that representative answers that call.
Some interest groups have even
more dedicated participants
that they can rely upon.
These can be people that are actually
paid for their time and effort,
or people that are just
so dedicated to the issue
that they really wanna be there
whenever that's necessary.
I'll give you an example.
The NRA is the National Rifle Association.
They have a lot of money.
They have direct access to politicians
that really want their endorsement
when it's time for an election,
and they've got a lot of members
that believe fervently
in the Second Amendment
and wanna do what the NRA says
in order to advance that legislation.
There's also something called movements.
They're not exactly issue groups
'cause they're not as organized
or as identifiable as
a group like the NRA,
but you can take a look at the
Black Lives Matter movement,
or the Me Too movement
to see a bunch of people
coming together and fighting for a concern
and an issue that's important to them.
These movements can be
very impactful as well,
as we saw in the summer of 2020
after to the murder of George Floyd.
So today we've looked at interest groups,
how they differ from
political action committees,
but how they're also very consequential.
We looked at the different types
and how they can be
different among themselves
in terms of the effect that they can have.
If you have an issue
that's important to you
I would suggest that you
find an interest group
and really see how you can be
an active member of our democracy.