- In previous lessons, we've
looked at campaign finance.
How campaigns are very expensive
and they need to gather
money from various areas
in order to actually fund themselves.
Today we're gonna look at PACs.
Also called political action committees.
These are when groups
of people come together
in order spot certain
candidates or legislation.
There's two different type of PACs
that I want you to be aware of.
Number one are called
separate segregated fund.
Also SSF.
This is an account that
is being used by a group
that is directly connected
to a candidate or a campaign.
Therefore, this money is
gonna be highly regulated.
On the other hand, we have
a non-connected committee
As you can see from the title,
this is a committee that
is not directly connected
to a candidate
and therefore it may
raise unlimited funds.
It should be noted though,
these non-connected committees
and super PACS in general,
even if they're not directly
connected to a candidate
are gonna look to what that
candidate that they support
and like wants to be done,
even by signaling and
then go in that path.
We're gonna look more to that now.
There's three different types of PACs
that we should really pay attention to.
Number one is called a super PAC.
They're much larger
and they're not limited
in how much money they
can raise and spend.
However, they must not directly
coordinate with campaigns.
That's why I'm talking
about that gray area.
They may not be in communication
overtly with the campaign
but they're gonna listen to
what the campaign is saying
and what they're pushing for
and what that campaign may need
in order to become the
one who wins the election.
And the super PAC is gonna
try to help in that effort.
Number two is called a hybrid PAC.
They're hybrid because they
have two separate bank accounts.
One that can coordinate
directly with the candidate
and one that cannot,
similar to the super PAC.
The last PAC we're gonna talk
about is leadership PACs.
These are controlled by a candidate
or an individual currently in office.
They're gonna support other candidates
or other people running for reelection.
And the other people that are
actually receiving the support
and the money aren't in control
of these leadership PACs.
So let break it down further.
I may be a Senator.
I control this leadership PAC.
I see another Senator
running for a reelection
and I like that Senator
and I wanna help them.
I can divert that money
from my leadership PAC
to that person's campaign.
The person that received the
funds cannot control that.
What I do, what I don't do,
but if they receive it that's fine.
They can use that money
to run for reelection.
So we've seen three
different types of PACs
and how they differ in
what they're allowed to do
and what not to do.
Let's look at how this money
has grown over the past years.
Within PACs, there'll
be two different types.
Dark money, refers to political
spending contributions
that are not disclosed.
So it's happening in the dark.
It's not transparent about
where this money is coming from,
who it's going to.
501s are nonprofit corporations.
So they're not being run to
actually benefit the people
who run that corporation
like a typical business
like Target or J.Crew would be.
They're doing it just
to advance their causes
that they think are important.
I want you to take a look at this graph.
What do you see that happened
after the 2010 decision
that the Supreme court had
in terms of Citizens United.
In 2004,
there was only $5 million, about,
in dark money spending.
By 2008 there was almost
70 million spending.
After citizens United,
there was $310 million
in dark money spending.
Where it's not clear where
that money's coming from
and who in particular it's going to.
That lack of transparency
is something that some people think
is a negative outta Citizens United.
But it makes it harder to
see who's influencing who,
who's got control over somebody
else via those donations.
So today we talked about
political action committees.
What they are, the different types
and how their influence has
grown since Citizens United.
It's important that you as
an active member of democracy
understand this.
Number one, so you can
contribute if you'd like,
but also so you can understand
where is the support for
a politician coming from
and is that having an undue influence
on their eventual actions?